

[ (+81) 80-3315-8649 | ■ 0x0@anirbanbasu.com | 🏠 https://www.anirbanbasu.com | 🛅 anirbanbasu

"There is only one corner of the universe you can be certain of improving, and that's your own self." – Aldous Huxley

# **Summary**

With more than a decade of research experience within both academia and industry, I have co-authored 70+ research papers and 30+ Japanese patents. My publications have been cited more than 2,000 times setting my overall h-index to 22 (source: Google Scholar). My current research is based on a user-empowering view of computational trust in human-machine interactions; and the role of computational trust in security and privacy. The areas of research that interest me include, but are not limited to: computational trust systems, Al security, Al ethics and causal modelling, distributed consensus, privacy and risk, and privacy preserving data mining. I like working on complex problems that require multi-disciplinary approaches. Outside research and the accompanying coding, I am keen on photography, videography and the associated travels.

# Professional experience.

Hitachi, Ltd. Yokohama, Japan

SENIOR RESEARCHER (APR. 2021 - PRESENT) AND RESEARCHER (OCT. 2018 - MAR. 2021); LECTURER (APR. 2022 - PRESENT)

Oct. 2018 - present

AT HITACHI ACADEMY

• Summary: Researcher, working on several research projects involving computational trust within the Hitachi Research & Development group. Also teaching about trust through Hitachi Academy.

Freelancer Tokvo, Japan

CONSULTANT Aug. 2014 – present

• Highlights: Open-source software development, web design and development, document design and photography.

KDDI Research, Inc. Fujimino, Japan

RESEARCH ENGINEER

ADJUNCT PROFESSOR

VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW

May. 2013 – Apr. 2018

• Highlights: Worked on a number of private and government funded projects on privacy, trust and security. Generated 30+ research publications and around 20 patents..

**Tokai University** Tokyo, Japan

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Oct. 2010 - Mar. 2013

• Highlights: Worked on a multi-institutional government funded JPY 500M+ project on privacy-preserving collaborative filtering.

**University of Sussex** 

ASSOCIATE TUTOR (OCT. 2004 - JAN. 2010) AND RESEARCH FELLOW (OCT. 2008 - SEP. 2009)

Brighton, UK Oct. 2004 – Jan. 2010

• Highlights: Re-developed a course module on electronic commerce technologies for the Masters degree programme funded by American Express. Worked in two (GBP 1M and GBP 1.4M) EPSRC funded research projects related to computational trust.

Freelancer Brighton, UK

TECHNOLOGY CONSULTANT (JUN. 2010 – SEP. 2010; JUL. 2005 – SEP. 2008)

Jul. 2005 - Sep. 2010

• Highlights: Technology consultant to the University of Sussex library. Developed Java Web Services hooks for Class Calendar Ltd. Codeveloped computational skills training videos for Claro Training Ltd.

**University of Sussex** Brighton, UK

RESEARCH ASSISTANT (SEP. 2003 – SEP. 2004) AND STEP UK SUMMER INTERN (Jul. 2003 – Aug. 2003)

Jul. 2003 – Sep. 2004

- Highlights: Developed a lightweight augmented reality based visualisation technology based on backend XML-based storage as part of a EUR 2.8M EU Framework Programme V funded project on digital cultural heritage.
- Award: Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP, UK) Local Finalist.

# Professional affiliations \_\_\_\_

**IFIP Trust Management (IFIPTM)** 

OntarioTech University Oshawa, Canada

Collaborative research with Dr. Peter Lewis and Dr. Stephen Marsh within the Faculty of Business and Information Technology.

**University of Sussex** 

HONORARY RESEARCH FELLOW (MAR. 2020 - PRESENT) AND VISITING RESEARCH FELLOW (JAN. 2010 - MAR. 2020)

Brighton, UK Jan. 2010 – present

Oct. 2022 - present

· Collaborative research with the Foundations of Software Systems (FoSS) group in the Department of Informatics.

Tokyo, Japan

SECRETARY (JUN. 2015 – PRESENT) AND PUBLICITY CHAIR (JUN. 2010 – JUN. 2015)

Jun. 2010 – present

• Contributing to the IFIP Working Group 11.11 – Trust Management (IFIPTM), the premier venue on computational trust management research.

**Rutgers University** Newark, NJ, USA

• Collaborative research with Prof. Jaideep Vaidya at the Rutgers Business School.

Oct. 2014 - Sep. 2017

## **Education**

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (D.PHIL.) IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE

Oct. 2004 - Feb. 2010

- Supervisors: Prof. Ian Wakeman and Dr. Dan Chalmers.
- Examiners: Dr. Des Watson (University of Sussex) and Prof. David Parish (Loughborough University)
- **Doctoral thesis:** 'A Reputation Framework for Behavioural History' proposed a high-level, generalised, policy-independent and context-aware framework to build and share reputations of network clients based on their behavioural history in order to inform future interactions. PDF: https://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-dphil2010.pdf.

University of Sussex

Brighton, UK

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING (B.ENG.) IN COMPUTER SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Oct. 2001 - Jun. 2004

- Grade: First Class Honours.
- Awards: (1) IEE Sussex Branch local prize for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.); and (2) the Eurotherm company prize for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project.
- Final year project: 'ARCOLite a visualisation system for viewing museum artefacts' presented a lightweight XML-based repository and a desktop visualisation in both virtual and augmented reality. PDF: https://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/thesis-beng2004.pdf.

# **Accolades**

#### INVITED TALKS

2018	<b>World Wide Web Foundation</b> , Privacy – connecting the dots	London, UK
2017	IFIP TM - Doctoral Symposium, Homomorphic Encryption - an answer to privacy?	Göteborg, Sweden
2015	<b>Kyushu University - Next Generation Cryptography</b> , Homomorphic Encryption – are we there yet?	Fukuoka, Japan
2012	<b>CSA - SecureCloud</b> , Practical privacy using homomorphic encryption – a myth or reality	Frankfurt, Germany

### **AWARDS**

2004	<b>IEE Sussex Branch local prize</b> , for Outstanding Performance in Computer Systems Engineering (B.Eng.)	Brighton, UK
2004	<b>Eurotherm company prize</b> , for Best Electrical, Electronic or Computer Systems Engineering project	Brighton, UK
2003	Local Finalist, Shell Technology Enterprise Programme (STEP)	Brighton, UK

#### **SCHOLARSHIPS**

2004	<b>Graduate Teaching Assistantship (2004–2007)</b> , Department of Informatics (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK
2001	<b>Dean's Bursary (2001–2004)</b> , Department of Engineering and Design (University of Sussex)	Brighton, UK

## **Publications**

A reverse chronological list of my publications is available at: https://www.anirbanbasu.com/files/publications-by-year.pdf.

#### **Research papers**

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] N. Dwyer, H. Miller-Bakewell, T. Darbyshire, **A. Basu**, and S. Marsh, "The ethical implications of using digital traces: studying explainability and trust during a pandemic," *Qualitative and Digital Research in Times of Crisis: Methods, Reflexivity, and Ethics*, p. 129, 2021.
- [2] S. Marsh, T. Atele-Williams, **A. Basu**, N. Dwyer, P. R. Lewis, H. Miller-Bakewell, and J. Pitt, "Thinking about Trust: People, Process, and Place," *Elsevier Cell Patterns*, vol. 1, June 2020.
- [3] **A. Basu**, M. S. Rahman, R. Xu, K. Fukushima, and S. Kiyomoto, "VIGraph A Framework for Verifiable Information," in *Proceedings of the IFIP WG 11.11 International Conference on Trust Management (IFIPTM)*, Göteborg, Sweden, 2017, pp. 12–20.
- [4] **A. Basu**, A. Monreale, R. Trasarti, J. C. Corena, F. Giannotti, D. Pedreschi, S. Kiyomoto, Y. Miyake, and T. Yanagihara, "A risk model for privacy in trajectory data," *Journal of Trust Management*, vol. 2, no. 1, pp. 1–23, 2015.
- [5] **A. Basu**, J. Vaidya, H. Kikuchi, and T. Dimitrakos, "Privacy-preserving collaborative filtering on the cloud practical implementation experiences," in *Proceedings of the IEEE Cloud*, Santa Clara, CA, USA, 2013.
- [6] **A. Basu**, S. Fleming, J. Stanier, S. Naicken, I. Wakeman, and V. K. Gurbani, "The state of peer-to-peer network simulators," *ACM Computing Surveys*, vol. 45, no. 4, pp. 46:1–46:25, 08 2013.

#### Patents and public information (total 32)

WIPO PATENTSCOPE PUBLICATION NUMBERS

2022102062, 2021170262, 2021089679, WO/2021/112216, 2020014056, 2019176264, 2019174995, 2019121946, 2019075619, 2018195907, 2018195154, 2018136625, 2018136626, 2018136627, 2018124924, 2018124513, 2018022258, 2017183932, 2017059872, 2017037180, 2016167705, 2016052047, 2016025563, 2016009243, 2015210795, 2015176496, 2015148907, 2015127859, 2015095671, 2015069350, 2015041863, 2015014958.

## Skills

OS: macOS, Windows, Linux, UNIX; Documents: MS Office, Google Docs and ETcX; Software development: Java, C#, Objective-C, Computing skills

C++, Visual C++, C, Visual Basic, XML, Javascript, UML, Subversion, Git, JUnit, Ant, Maven, MySQL, JBoss, Tomcat, Google App

Engine, Amazon Elastic Beanstalk. (Non-exhaustive list.)

**Languages** English (fluent), Bengali (native), Japanese (intermediate), Hindi (elementary)

UPDATED: OCTOBER 30, 2022 ANIRBAN BASU | CURRICULUM VITÆ 2 OF 2